<para> After being loaded in, medical images can be manipulated in a
  variety of ways with AMIDE.  An important point to remember is that
  AMIDE deals with all data sets as 3 or 4 dimensional data sets.
  While 2D slices extracted from the the data set are displayed on the
  computer screen, at no time does AMIDE handle images as anything
  less than 3 dimensional data.</para>




<sect2><title>Manipulating Data Sets on Screen</title>

  <sect3><title>Displaying Data Sets</title>

  <para> When initially loaded into the program, a data set is not
    displayed on the canvases.  Rather, the name of the data set is
    contained in the study list, and the user needs to select the data
    set in the study list so that it is displayed on the
    canvases. </para>
  
  <para> Displaying multiple data sets is as simple as importing more
    than one data set, and then selecting the data sets that you wish
    to view from the study list. </para>

  <para> The time period over which the slices are drawn is determined
    by the time dialog, described in more detail in <xref
    linkend="frame-dialog" /> </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3><title>Pertinent Mouse Actions</title>

   <para> The following mouse actions can be used when the mouse is
   hovering over a data set on any of the orthogonal views</para>

   <variablelist>

     <varlistentry><term>Shift-Left Mouse Button</term> 
     <listitem><para> This combination allows shifting of the active
       data set in space (usually used for aligning two data sets).
       While holding the shift key, left click (and release) on the
       canvas, and you'll grab the active data set. You can now shift
       the active data around on the canvas.  At this point, to enact
       the shift, click the right button (button 3).  Any other mouse
       button will cancel the shift action.  </para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Shift-Right Mouse Button</term> 
     <listitem><para> This combination allows rotating of the active
	data set in space (usually used for aligning two data sets).
	While holding the shift key, middle click (and release) on the
	canvas, and you'll grab the active data set. You can now
	rotate the active data around on the canvas.  At this point,
	to enact the rotation, click the right button (button 3).  Any
	other mouse button will cancel the rotation.</para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term>Ctrl-Right Mouse Button</term>
     <listitem><para> This combination will place an alignment point
        at the current cursor location.  A dialog will popup for entry
        of the alignment point's name.</para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

   </variablelist>


  </sect3>
  

</sect2>

<sect2 id="manual_alignment"><title>Manually Aligning Data Sets</title>

  <para> What follows is a quick guide to manually aligning data sets
  in AMIDE</para>

  <procedure>
    <step>
      <para>
	First rotate each of the data sets so that they are level with
	respect to the transverse, coronal, and sagittal views.  This is
        easily done using the shift-2 mouse combination, but 
        can also be done from the data set modification dialog.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
	Choose one of the data sets to be the active data set.  The other
        data set will be the "fixed" data set.  
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
	Shift the active data set so that the two data sets line up appropriately.
        This is easily done using the shift-1 mouse combination, but can also be
        done from the data set modification dialog.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        If fine tuning adjustments are needed, these are best done from the
        data set modification dialog.
      </para>
    </step>
  </procedure>          
  
</sect2>


<sect2 id="data-set-dialog"><title>Data Set Modification Dialog</title>

    <para> To modify parameters of a data set, right click on the name
      of the data set in the study tree to pop-up the data set
      modification dialog box.  Parameters that can be modified are
      divided into the following pages. </para>

   <variablelist>    

    <varlistentry><term>Basic Info</term>
      <listitem><para>

	On this page are options to alter the data set name, type of
	modality, subject name, subject id, subject date of birth
	(DOB), conversion factor, and the interpolation type to use
	for this data set (described at <xref linkend="interpolation"
	/>).  The conversion factor is a parameter that is multiplied
	to the data set before it is used for viewing or quantitation.
	Since the data set is in ECAT/MAP/abitrary scale units, the
	conversion factor can be used in order to analyze the data set
	in another type of reference unit (e.g. Percent Injected Dose
	[%ID]).  There is also a built in calculator, where parameters
	such as subject weight and injected dose can be entered, and
	the conversion factor will be generated.  Note that 1 cc is
	assumed to equal 1 g when generating the %ID/g and SUV.

      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    <varlistentry><term>Center</term>
      <listitem><para>
	The data set can be shifted by respecifing the center of the
	data set with respect to the origin.  The x, y, and z
	dimensions are in millimeters.
	</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Voxel Size</term>
      <listitem><para>
        The size of the data set's voxels (again, in millimeters) can
	be altered on this page.  The "keep aspect ratio" button
	specifies that when altering the size of any voxel component
	(x, y, or z), the relative sizes between the components should
	be kept the same.
	</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Rotate</term>
      <listitem><para>
	The data set can be rotated around its center in this page.
        There is one dial for each of the three slice planes.  The
        transverse dial will spin the data set in the transverse plane
        (i.e. rotate on the z-axis).  The coronal dial will spin the
        data set in the coronal plane (i.e. rotate on the y-axis).
        And the sagittal dial will spin the data set in the sagittal
        plane (i.e. rotate on the x-axis).  The "reset to default"
        button allows the data set to be rotated back to the default
        orientation.  On the bottom of this page is a matrix showing
        the coordinate frame of the data set with respect to the base
        coordinate frame.
	</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    <varlistentry><term>Colormap/Threshold</term>
      <listitem><para>
	This page is analogous to the thresholding tool dialog
	(described at <xref linkend="threshold_dialog" />) above).  
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry><term>Time</term>
      <listitem><para>
	From this page, the timing information of the data set can be
	altered.  Scan start time can be used for altering the start
	time of the scan with respect to other data sets.  Corrections
	in the duration of each data frame can also be made on this
	page. </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry><term>Windowing Preferences</term>
    <listitem><para>
      The max and min threshold levels used for the bone and soft
      tissue CT window buttons can be explicitly set here.  The
      "Insert Current Thresholds" button will reset the max and min
      values with the data set's currently used threshold levels.  
     </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    <varlistentry><term>Immutables</term>
      <listitem><para>
	This panel lists information about the data set that cannot be
	altered.  The underlying internal data format of the data set
	and the data set dimensions in voxels are displayed on this
	page.
	</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
</sect2>


  


