<para> 

  AMIDE saves studies in an extensible XML based directory format
  called XIF (Xml Image Format).  These data directories
  characteristically end with ".xif", and appear as files within
  AMIDE.

</para>
  
<sect1><title>Format of Saved Studies</title>

  <para>
    Although admittedly annoying from a data transfer standpoint,
    using a directory structure for saving study information has the
    decisive advantage of making the saved information easily
    accessible using standard command-line utilities and text-based
    tools.
  </para>

  <para>
    Each XIF directory contains a file called "Study.xml" which
    contains the basic study parameters.  Additional files can also be
    found in the XIF directory, such as ROI_*.xml files which contain
    ROI's, and Volume_*.xml files and their corresponding Volume_*.dat
    files, which contain the image data set parameters and the raw
    data respectively.  The raw data file format is arbitrary, and is
    little endian 32-bit float by default.
  </para>


</sect1>


<sect1><title>Opening Studies</title>
  
  <para>
    
    From the main window, select "File->Open", and a file selection
    widget will open up.  Select an XIF filename in the right column,
    and then hit the "OK" button (or double click on the filename).  

  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>Saving Studies</title>
  <para>

    To save a study, from the study window select "File->Save As" and
    a file selection dialog will appear.  Look at the "selection:"
    line near the bottom of the window, if this is the desired XIF
    filename, hit "OK" and the file will be saved.  If this is not
    the desired XIF filename, select or enter in the correct XIF
    study, and hit the "OK" button.

  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1><title>Exporting a View</title>
  <para>

    To export one of the views (transverse/coronal/sagittal) to an
    external image file, select "File->Export View->[view]" from the
    menu.  The saved data format is jpeg.

  </para>
</sect1>
  
  
  <!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
  Local variables:
  mode: sgml
  sgml-omittag:t
  sgml-shorttag:t
  sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
  sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
  sgml-indent-step:2
  sgml-indent-data:t
  sgml-parent-document:nil
  sgml-exposed-tags:nil
  sgml-local-catalogs:nil
  sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
  End:
  -->            
