
<para> AMIDE stands for Amide's a Medical Image Data Examiner.  This
program is a tool for viewing and analyzing volumetric medical imaging
data sets, and has been designed from the ground up with support for
multi-modality imaging.
</para>
  

<sect2><title>Licensing</title>

  <para>AMIDE is released under the terms of the <ulink type="http"
  url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html">GNU General Public
  Library (GPL).</ulink></para>

  <para>The text of the license is fairly verbose.  A quick summary
  follows:
  </para>

  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You are free to run the program, for any purpose.  Please note
     that, although the GPL makes no restrictions on use of the
     program, your government probably does.  For instance, in the
     United States, AMIDE is not FDA approved and cannot be used
     clinically.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You are free to study the source code of the program, and adapt
     it to your needs.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You are free to redistribute the program.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You are free to release modified versions of the program, as long
     as you also redistribute the source code to the modified program,
     and you label your modified version of the program appropriately.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist> 




</sect2>

<sect2><title>Availability of Source Code</title>

  <para> The source code for AMIDE is readily available from the
  <ulink type="http" url="http://amide.sourceforge.net">AMIDE web
  site</ulink>.
  </para>

</sect2>


<sect2><title>Supported Platforms</title>

  <para> In addition to source code, binary versions of AMIDE along
  with installation instructions can be found for several systems on
  the <ulink type="http" url="http://amide.sourceforge.net">AMIDE web
  site</ulink>.  The currently supported systems are Linux/i386,
  Microsoft Windows, and Macintosh OS X (achieved through the use of
  the <ulink type="http"
  url="http://fink.sourceforge.net">fink</ulink> add-on packages).
  </para>

</sect2>

  
<sect2><title>Contact Information</title>

    <para> Questions and bug reports can be addressed to the AMIDE
    users list <email> amide-users@lists.sourceforge.net</email>.
    Information on joining the list and/or viewing archived messages
    can be found <ulink type="http"
    url="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=9464">here</ulink>.
    </para> 

</sect2>
