<para> 
  
  ROI stands for Region of Interest.  ROI's designate a volume on
  the object over which statistics should be calculated.
  
</para>
  


<sect2><title>ROI Types</title>
  
  <para>
    The following ROI types are currently supported.
  </para>
  
  <sect3><title>Ellipsoid</title>
    <para>
      An ellipsoid is similar to a sphere, but with a radius
      specified for each direction [x,y,z].  In the case of x=y=z,
      the ellipsoid is a sphere.
    </para>
  </sect3>
  
  <sect3><title>Elliptic Cylinder</title>
    <para>
      An elliptic cylinder is similar to a regular cylinder, except
      it has an ellipse as it's base instead of a circle.
    </para>
  </sect3>
  
  <sect3><title>Box</title>
    <para>
	Exactly what it says, a 3D box.
    </para>
  </sect3>
  
  <sect3><title>Isocontours</title>
    <para>
      Isocontour ROI's are regions selected from the data set such
      that the edge values of the ROI are always the same value.
      There are two types, 2D and 3D isocontours.
    </para>
    
    <sect4><title>2D Isocontour</title>
      <para>
	A 2D isocontour is derived by considering a value on one of
	the displayed 2D slices.  The depth of a 2D isocontour is
	specified initially by the depth of the viewed slices.
      </para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4><title>3D Isocontour</title>
      <para>
	A 3D isocontour is derived by considering a value on the
	current frame of the active data set.
      </para>
    </sect4>
    
    </sect3>
  
  
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Drawing ROI's</title>
  
  <para>
    To draw an ROI, first select the ROI desired under the "add ROI:"
    pull down menu.  Amide will request a name for this ROI and add it
    to the study item list, but no ROI will be drawn.  The next mouse
    input on the displayed views will be used to draw the new ROI.
    For ellipsoid, elliptic cylinder, and box ROI's, The x and y
    dimensions of the ROI are controlled by the size of the drawing.
    The z dimension ("depth") of the newly drawn ROI is determined by
    the current image thickness.  For isocontour's, the value of the
    data set at the clicked upon location will be used to derive the
    isocontour.
  </para>
    
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Manipulating ROI's</title>
  
  <para>
    After an ROI is drawn, it can be further manipulated to adjust
    it's size, placement, and orientation.  You can directly
    manipulate the ROI by clicking on it in any of the viewing
    windows.  Mouse button 1 is used to shift ROIs.  Mouse button 2 is
    used to rotate ellipsoid, elliptic cylinder, and box ROIs, and for
    erasing points from isocontour ROI's.  Mouse button 3 is used for
    zooming ellipsoid, elliptic cylinder and box ROI, and is used for
    redefining the isocontour value for isocontour ROI's.
    
    You can also edit the ROI size/placement/orientation/name etc. by
    clicking on mouse button 3 while over the ROI's name in the study
    item list.  This brings up the edit ROI dialog, which allows
    keyboard entry of the ROI's parameters.

  </para>
    
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Calculating Statistics over ROI's</title>

  <para>
    Statistics on an ROI can be calculated via the analysis menu.
    Choosing "All" will calculate all the ROI's on the currently
    selected images.  Choosing "Selected" will calculate the selected
    ROI's on the currently selected images.
  </para>
  
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Gotcha's to ROI calculations </title>
  
  <sect3><title>Variance/Std. Dev./Std. Err. Fallacies</title>
    
    <para>
      A common fallacy is to use the calculated variance (or standard
      deviation, or standard error) of an ROI as an experiment's
      variance.  The variance of an experiment can only truly be
      measured by taking multiple samples (i.e. performing multiple
      scans) and calculating the variance between these different
      samples.  The variance that AMIDE calculates is only a measure
      of the noise within an ROI in the given data set.
    </para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3><title>Changing Calculated Volume</title> 
    <para> 
	AMIDE calculates ROI's by translating the ROI's dimensions into the
	data set's coordinate space.  It then computes statistics for all the
	data set voxels that are in the ROI.  For voxels that lie on
	the edge of the ROI, AMIDE will subdivide the voxel into a finite
	number of subvoxels, and calculate over the subvoxels.  This approach
	yields correct statistics, but it is important to realize that the
	computed ROI is a discrete representation of the specified analytical
	ROI.  So while the true volume of an ellipse is pi*r1*r2*r3, the
	computed volume of the ellipse in AMIDE will depend on the number of
	voxels and subvoxels that were determined to line within the ellipse,
	which in turn can depend on the orientation of the ROI.  Since the
	computed volume given by AMIDE represents the volume in the data set
	that was used for the ROI calculation, you will want to use that value
	(not the real ellipse value).
    </para>
  </sect3>

</sect2>

  
  
  <!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
  Local variables:
  mode: sgml
  sgml-omittag:t
  sgml-shorttag:t
  sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
  sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
  sgml-indent-step:2
  sgml-indent-data:t
  sgml-parent-document:nil
  sgml-exposed-tags:nil
  sgml-local-catalogs:nil
  sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
  End:
  -->            
