 <para> The "Study object" in AMIDE is used for grouping a set of
 related data sets and ROI's.  Note that the use of the word "Study"
 here diverges from the traditional nuclear medicine use of the word,
 in which study generally connotates a single scan (or occasionally
 multiple but highly coupled scans) done on a single patient.  A study
 in AMIDE is often used to group an entire experiment (several
 patients, several animals, whatever) into a single file.  The study
 object itself is used mostly for storing parameters that effect all
 other objects stored in the study.</para>

<sect2 id="study-dialog"><title>Study Modification Dialog</title>

    <para> Similarly to the data set and ROI modification dialogs, the
      study modification dialog can be used to alter parameters
      relevant to the entire study.  Right click on the name of the
      study in the study tree to pop-up the study modification dialog
      box.  Parameters that can be modified are divided into the
      following pages. </para>

   <variablelist>    

    <varlistentry><term>Basic Info</term>
      <listitem><para>
	On this page are options to alter the name and creation date of the study.
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    <varlistentry><term>View Center</term>
      <listitem><para>
        From this page, the point that the study is currently viewing 
        can be explicitly changed.  The x, y, and z
	dimensions are in millimeters.
	</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>Rotate</term>
      <listitem><para>
	The entire study (including all objects within it) can be
        rotated around the view center in this page.  There is one
        dial for each of the three slice planes.  The transverse dial
        will spin the study in the transverse plane (i.e. rotate on
        the z-axis).  The coronal dial will spin the study in the
        coronal plane (i.e. rotate on the y-axis).  And the sagittal
        dial will spin the study in the sagittal plane (i.e. rotate
        on the x-axis).  The "reset to default" button allows the study
        to be rotated back to the default orientation.  On the
        bottom of this page is a matrix showing the coordinate frame
        of the study with respect to the base coordinate frame.
        </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry><term>ROI/View Preferences</term>
     <listitem><para>
	The width of the line used to draw geometric ROIs can be
	altered here (1-5 pixels).  This parameter is not relevant for
	isocontour ROI's.
     </para><para>
	Canvas layout allows you to switch the three views
	(transverse, coronal, and sagittal) between a linear style
	layout more commonly seen in PET software, and an orthogonal
	style layout more commonly seen in MRI software.  "Maintain
	view size constant" allows you to pick if you want the size of
	the view to remain constant or not.  If not checked, the size
	of the views shown will depend only on the data sets selected.
	If the checkbox is checked, the size of the views will depend
	on all the data sets in the study.  Finally, "target empty
	area" is for setting the size of the empty area in the middle
	of the target (the crosshairs on the views when changing the
	view location).
     </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    
    <varlistentry><term>Immutables</term>
      <listitem><para>
	This panel lists information about the study that cannot be
	altered.  "Voxel dim" is the preferred voxel dimension, this
	is what the canvas will use as the "basic" voxel dimension,
	from which the zoom factor is relative too.
	</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

 </sect2>

    



