

<sect2><title>Alignment Wizard</title>

  <para>In addition to manually aligning data sets (described at <xref
  linkend="manual_alignment" />), data sets can also be aligned using
  the alignment wizard.  The process is basically:</para>
  
  <procedure>
    <step>
      <para>
       Draw at least three pairs of fiducial makers between the two
       data sets that you wish to align.  Drawing fiducial markers is
       described below as <xref linkend="fiducial-marker" />.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
       Run the alignment wizard (under tools->alignment wizard).  For
       the alignment wizard to recognize two fiducial markers as a
       pair, they must have exactly the same name.  So if you have a
       marker labeled "1" under the first data set, you will need
       another marker, also labeled "1", under the second data set.
      </para>
    </step>
  </procedure>          
  

  <sect3 id="fiducial-marker"><title>Drawing Fiducial Markers</title>
   <para>
    Fiducial markers can be added to any of the data sets in the study
    in a variety of ways.  For the currently active data set, hitting
    the "Edit->Add fiducial mark" menu item will drop a fiducial maker
    at the currently viewed location.  Fiducial marks can be added for
    the active data set directly from the views by pressing ctrl-right
    mouse button, which will drop a fiducial marker at the point that
    the mouse is currently at.  Finally, fiducial markers can be added
    to non-active data sets by pressing ctrl-right mouse button while
    hovering over a data set's name in the study list.</para>

   <para>After being created, the fiducial marker can be moved by
    clicking on the marker point shown in any of the views.
   </para>
 </sect3>

 <sect3 id="fiducial-marker-dialog"><title>Fiducial Marker Modification Dialog Box</title>
  <para>
      To modify parameters of a fiducial mark, right click the point
      in the study list to pop-up the Fiducial Marker Modification
      Dialog.  From this dialog, the name and location of the fiducial
      marker can be altered.
  </para>
    
 </sect3>

</sect2>


<sect2><title>Crop Wizard</title> 

  <para>Coming soon.  Note that only what is strictly inside the
   cursor lines is saved.  What's underneath and outside the cursor
   lines is cropped away. </para>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Factor Analysis Wizard</title>
   <para>The factor analysis wizard is currently being developed.  It
   probably won't work for you, and is only included in AMIDE for
   those who might be interested in working on it (rather than with
   it).</para>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Filter Wizard</title>
   <para>Nothing written yet...</para>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>Fly Through Wizard</title>
   <para>Nothing written yet...</para>
   <para> Note, will generally get much better results for fly through
   if using trilinear interpolation.</para>
</sect2>


<sect2 id="profile-dialog"><title>Profile Tool</title>
 <para>Nothing written yet...</para>
</sect2>


<sect2><title>ROI Statistics</title>
   <para>A description of the ROI statistics tool can be found at:
   <xref linkend="roi_statistics" />.</para>
</sect2>




